to understand how the multi-level page
table save space let's look at an
example of a simple and small twole page
table in this example we will use a very
small virtual address where we have an
offset and the page number and each of
these is four bits so using a flat page
table we would need 2 to the 4th entries
in it one for each possible page number
so the entries would be numbered 0
through 15 and we would index with our
page number here and get our frame
number with a two level page table let's
say we split this 4bit page number into
two 2bit pieces so the same virtual
address still has a 4-bit page number
that we split into two 2bit pieces the
outer part of the page number is used to
index into a four entry outer page table
and each entry in this outer page table
can point to a four entry inner page
table so in total we have four inner
page tables once we find the pointer to
the correct one we can use the inner
part of the page number to tell us which
entry to use and that gives us our frame
number so as indicated
previously the total size of all the
inner page tables here is the same as
the original size of the flat page table
here we had 16 entries here we have four
* 4 entries here Plus we added the space
for the outer page table so where are
the savings the savings are in that if
there is an unused large part of the
address space such that all of these
entries do not correspond to physical
memory then we don't need this and we
can Mark here in the outer page table
that the entry is not necessary and then
we can eliminate this inner page table
in a large address space the outer page
table table will have many pointers most
of which will point to Inner page tables
like this so we eliminate them so we end
up having one reasonably large outer
page table but one that we can fit in
memory and a small number of inner page
tables Each of which is reasonably sized
and fits in memory but we don't have
most of the inner page tables so we save
a lot of space